[Music]
thank you
foreign
and today we're gonna talk about Manipur
the Manipur crisis I'm going to take a
bunch of questions that you've asked and
hopefully that covers the entire gamut
of issues and topics related to this
matter but before we do that let's go
and see who all is there with us uh who
all is there on the live chat Allah
Snorlax the alkane Arcane self Vishnu
Mohan Nishant ketan pinky Kumari
chandana
Pratap Singh akshat arj sushant the
global stories GK
foreign
[Music]
and lots and lots of other people thank
you so much for being on the live stream
I will not be able to greet you all
individually but thank you so much for
being here
and uh with that said let's talk about
uh Manipur
so I have deliberately kept quiet about
Manipur for for a very long time the
issue began in early May
3rd of May and I kept quiet about this
because it's a sensitive matter
and now you have all kinds of stories on
social media and YouTube and whatever
God knows where with all kinds of
narratives and interpretations about
what's happening obviously there's a lot
of propaganda obviously there's a lot of
misinformation
so I think it's it's time now to you
know set set the matter right uh when it
comes to Manipur you know
I have
I have been studying the history of
Mongolia and chingis Khan since 1998.
when it comes to Manipur I've been
studying Manipur since 1997. that's more
than a quarter Century so I have some
understanding of Manipur and I have been
there more than once so
I understand the place I know the place
it's not like I am I I've read a couple
of Articles and I'm I'm you know
passing some judgment okay so with that
said let us begin with the questions
whatever yeah can you please explain the
origin of Manipur like when and how was
it established and where does its school
of thought belong to do shed some light
and what's the reason behind the
diversity of Manipur okay
first of all let's see where Manipur is
on the map we have to have the map right
so let's go to the maps and see where
Manipur is in case some of us are not
aware it's possible because our
education system completely ignores the
Northeast so we may not be aware of
where it is so this here is India As We
Know
and
if you go to the Far East of India we
have what we call the Northeast why is
it called the Northeast by the way it's
because the British first established
their foothold in Bengal of India which
is presented West Bengal and presented
Bangladesh unified Bengal the British
first colonized that place the bengalis
are the oldest colonized Indians when it
comes to the British colonization and
from their perspective in Bengal
from the British perspective in Bengal
the region that we call the Northeast
was to the northeast of Bengal
so they call it the Northeast the
northeastern territories or whatever and
afterwards our historians Etc
you know dutifully enslavishly kept on
calling this region the Northeast even
though it is actually the Far East of
India it is the northeast of Bengal but
the Far East of India but we still call
it the Northeast even though it is not
in the north east of India it's in the
Far East so that's the first ridiculous
thing and that we are still continuing
even to the to the media or your
teachers the professors your textbooks
they will all say the Northeast it's not
the Northeast it's the Far East
um
so here you have Manipur all right and
the capital of Manipur is the city of
imphal
so this is the state now what's the
origin of Manipur so the origin of
Manipur is not exactly known when it
began manipuri culture civilization the
people the manipuri people according to
some versions The the Manipur kingdom is
about 2000 years old according to other
versions it's at least three and a half
thousand years old what we can agree
upon what all history textbooks before
written before 2000 2000 will agree upon
is that the kingdom of Manipur is at
least 2000 years old all right and they
have this recorded lineage of kings and
this Royal Chronicle is called the
catharal kumbaba uh so we know the
history of Manipur we know how old it is
at least 2000 years old and
let's go to the satellite image so as
you can see it's it's all Hills uh
Manipur this region is in the foothills
of the Himalayas it's a very hilly Place
uh it's it's heavily forested and there
is uh the the valley region which itself
is a very high altitude region almost
900 meters above sea level the imfal
valley region
and the state is a Hill State so
about 2000 years ago or depending on
what what perspective you see two
thousand or three and a half thousand
years ago the entire in Fall Valley
region was uh you know was was uh
uh it was underwater essentially and
then the water slowly receded and the
first region
in the valley that became dry is called
the kangla which you will see deep
inside in Fall the kangla fort this is
the uh historical birthplace you could
say of of the manipuri uh Kingdom so
it's at least two thousand years old and
this the kangla fort is the Heartland or
the birthplace so to say of the manipuri
kingdom and manipuri culture and
civilization
so uh let's understand the origin of
Manipur little deeper so there is
something I have spoken about this but
let me say it again there is something
called the manipuri language that is
about 2000 years old at least everybody
knows the manipuri language what it is
it's the official state language of
Manipur it's around 2000 years old at
least now the question is which is the
ethnic group that is the originator of
the manipuri language today in Manipur
there are three major ethnic groups the
so-called nagas the so-called cookies
and the matis so of out of these three
ethnic groups which ethnic group is the
originator of the manipuri language the
answer is the Mathes not the nagas not
the cookies it is
um when it comes to the kings of Manipur
at least 2000 years of History the
recorded history of the kings of Manipur
they all belonged to just one ethnic
group and that was again the methes
uh there is something called manipuri
Dance that is world famous it's one of
the major dance forms of India uh it you
know a very distinctive unique uh style
of dance which is the ethnic group that
is the originator of manipuri dance once
again it's not the cookies or anybody
else it's the methods Manipur gave the
World the game of Polo the world's
oldest polo ground in the world
is in the city of imphal let me see if I
can locate it
let's search for it
imphalo ground it's somewhere in the
vicinity there we are
so
somewhere here
I think it's this one the polo ground
yeah this is the world's oldest polo
ground the question is which ethnic
group gave the World the game of Polo
once again it is the method so you can
see a pattern here when it comes to
manipuri martial arts when it comes to
any aspect of manipuri culture or
history or civilization when it comes to
the archaeological record of Manipur it
is all the history of the metis then
it's at least two thousand years old
okay so the point is that the methods
are The Originators of the manipuri
Kingdom the manipuri culture the
civilization the language everything
and the other ethnic group that is the
that is also indigenous to Manipur is
the people that we now call the nagas
there they are a group of
a large group
of Hill tribes very uh you know tribal
people who live in the Hills so the
history is that initially everybody in
Manipur
lived in the Hills initially like as in
at least 2000 years ago when the the
valley region was underwater everybody
lived in the Hills
then once the valley started drying out
some some of the manipuri uh the the
people uh settled in the valley and some
chose to stay in the Hills but they were
the same people
and over the past 2000 years there have
been cultural changes linguistic changes
so that's that's the origin of the Naga
method dichotomy but they are still
originally the same people they are the
descendants of the same ancestors the
nagas and the Mathis
so the lagas are equally indigenous to
this region the kingdom of Manipur was
way larger in the past uh
you know today uh today it is I mean
let's let's go back to the screen
yeah this is Manipur today the state of
Manipur it was in the past much larger
there was a king called kagemba in the
16th or 17th century who conquered parts
of Yunnan in China so the Manipur
Kingdom extended all the way to Yunnan
parts of unan and China in the past the
parts of nagaland President nagar and
were part of Manipur parts of Burma were
part of Manipur right so if you see the
city of for example Mandalay in Burma so
I showed you the the uh
I showed you the kangla fort in info
let's let's go to that again
so this is what remains of the kangla
fort it's about 2000 years old it's
roughly a square kind of or rectangular
kind of structure it has a moot and it
is protected by river the imphal river
it has a fort and all that now let's go
to the city of Mandalay in Burma
uh where is manly
here is Mandalay all right let's go to
Mandalay
now let's go to the satellite image
there is a fort in Mandalay The Mandalay
Palace it's about two three hundred
years old or so roughly you can look up
how old it is it is essentially a
replica a more modern replica of the
kangla fort in imphal which tells you
how influential manipuri culture was
even in Burma how influential Manipur is
a kingdom was even in Burma
so that's kind of the origin of Manipur
the manipuri Kings had excellent
relations with the neighboring Kingdom
tripura Assam uh even Burma Etc they
they married among these these various
kingdoms and all that uh you know that's
the kind of uh origin story that Manipur
has so historically it's King its
territorial boundaries extended Way
Beyond what we have today is the state
of Manipur the state of Manipur in its
present form is because of the British
uh occupation of India of Manipur and
what they delineated as a territorial
boundaries of Manipur so that's kind of
the origin story of Manipur the origin
the history of the origin of Manipur and
the reason behind the diversity of
Manipur there are so many different
tribes in Manipur Hill tribes and then
you have the methes who live who now are
forcibly confined to do to six percent
of the state Valley
so you have lots of different tribes who
are now classified as nagas Naga is an
umbrella term it's not their own
language it is the British who gave this
term to the to them and they classified
them as nagas there are lots of
different tribes among the nagas as well
the angami nagas
and so on and so forth lots of different
tribes some of them don't even speak the
same language but they are classified as
nagas but originally if you go back two
two and a half maybe three thousand
three and a half thousand years they all
descend from the same ancestral uh
population
so that is the origin of Manipur that's
how it was established uh School of
thoughts well uh the nagas had their own
polytheistic culture you know the the
you had elements of animism you know
elements of nature worship your elements
of ancestor worship it was a
polytheistic culture that was the
original beautiful nagarculture it's
been smashed out of existence then the
nagas are almost entirely exclusively
Christian now uh some Naga tribal groups
uh such as the well if you would call
the kabui as a Naga group then they are
still Hindus but yeah the original
culture was smashed out of them by the
British
and then today they have they they feel
no Affinity to their original culture
they are taught to believe that it was
primitive and backward and barbaric and
and things like that you know standard
practice standard Colonial practice of
imposing foreign religion and then
making people ashamed feel ashamed of
their ancestral culture so uh that is
about the um
ancestral original culture of the nagas
when it comes to the Mathis or their
natural original uh if you would call it
religion it is called Sanam in English
so it is a once again a very uh complex
polytheistic culture and about well as
you can see Manipur is kind of at the
crossroads between uh the Indian
subcontinent in Southeast Asia Indian
subcontinent was obviously Hindu and
Buddhist and Southeast Asia was also a
Hindu and Buddhist so obviously Manipur
would have influences of all these
things uh so the oldest known record of
Hinduism in Manipur dates back to the I
think 7th or 8th Century A.D
um there is this copper plate
inscription or something of a manipuri
king with Sanskrit words in the names of
uh various gods and goddesses that sort
of thing Hindu gods and goddesses
the oldest Hanuman I think Hanuman
Temple in Manipur go dates back to the
12th or 13th century in the 18th century
there was this big flowering of
vaishnavism in Manipur so today most
manipuri is the either I would say they
practice a mix of the ancestral culture
salamaism and Hinduism elements of both
kind of like Japan where everybody
whoever is still religious practices
elements of Shinto as well as Buddhism
Hinduism that sort of thing
so that's uh and and now see the the
British tried to christianize the the
state of Manipur the nagaland ETC the
nagas the misos down south they were
christianized rapidly the myth is
resisted for decades after Independence
1947 Manipur merged with India in 1949
after Independence uh the the Indian
government the nehruvian regime brought
in lots of American missionaries to
christianize the the Far East of India
the meth is still resisted but today in
the past 20 or so years the methods have
started giving up and today there are
about two or three lakh methane
Christians so the methods are also
giving up and they're also becoming
christianized but so that's the thing
so that's the story of Manipur the
history of Manipur the origin of the
Kingdom uh the diversity the schools of
thought the religion all of that I hope
that uh throws some light on on the
history and the culture of the place
no
next question is by Gautam why did the
British Force the manipuri king uh
excuse me so settle Burmese Nationals
into Manipur
where did the British Force the Manipur
again to settle Burmese Nationals into
Manipur okay so the British
so we have to understand when does
Britain come into the picture uh we know
that the British uh the last 300 or so
years about 300 or so years ago they had
uh they had started colonizing India uh
their first foothold was in Bengal
present-day West Bengal and Bangladesh
unified Bengal and then what happened is
in the 18th century you had this great
flowering of vaishnava culture in
Manipur a great uh era of cultural
efflorescence and all that then in the
beginning of the 19th century things
went bad the royal succession was messed
up there was infighting for succession
for becoming the next king there was
political disunity there was political
instability and I think it was the year
1819 that the Burmese invaded and
conquered Manipur Burma as you can see
is south of Manipur very large uh
Kingdom today is a country Myanmar Burma
so the Burmese
King invaded Manipur successfully in
1819 and occupied Manipur for seven
years so from 1819 to 1826 approximately
if I'm if I recall correctly the Burmese
occupied Manipur it was a disastrous
time for Manipur they took incredible
amounts numbers of manipuri prisoners of
war and they settled them in they took
them to Burma to use them as slave labor
their descendants still lived there
today you know Burmese mateys who still
practice their culture lots of manipuris
methods were forced to escape to parts
of Assam to tripura and so on just to
survive those are the and you know even
even Bengal uh you could say places like
silhat Etc
so this is the origin of the Vishnu
Priya mateys who live outside of
present-day Manipur
and Manipur was devastated so it's
called seven years of devastation
from 1819 to 1826 eventually the
manipuri King was able to take control
of Manipur again but he had to turn to
the British for protection because the
Burmese threat was always there and that
is the entry of the British into
manipuri into Manipur and essentially
Manipur then became a British
protectorate of British puppet of
British vasal State that's what happened
the British would uh they installed a
political agent
in the court of the manipuri king and
that's where everything started going
bad
so um the British
there were also uh expanding into Burma
and all that so there is a place called
chin State let's go and see chin State
chin state
uh well what not China State chin state
okay so this shaded region is chin State
and that's where you have the zoo people
you know the chin zo people zochin
whatever you want to call them it's a
tribal group it's a bunch of tribes one
of the tribes is called
there are other tribes as well it's an
agglomeration or whatever you want to
call it of uh reasonably closely related
tribes and they are not Burmese by the
way they don't speak the Burmese
language but the Burmese language is is
not something they speak they don't
practice Burmese culture the Burmese are
they have historically been Hindu and
Buddhist today it's called a Buddhist
Nation well the the chin people are not
Buddhists they don't speak the Burmese
language they don't practice Burmese
culture and they're essentially fighting
a war for secession from Burma
separatism
so the British ventured into this region
and they started settling
uh these Burmese Nationals in small
numbers in Manipur uh they said that
these guys are going to help us as
Porters and all that they're gonna be
you know they're gonna do some uh labor
work for us and things like that
and uh the term they used for these
people was coolies but then it morphed
into cookies
right so the original the origin
of the word cookie is is
so then the British started settling
them in Manipur why did they want to
settle these Outsiders these foreigners
into Manipur it was to the classic
tactic of divide and Rule
so you see the British started
exercising a significant amount of
influence and control over the manipuri
kingdom
or the policies of the manipuri king and
everybody could see what's happening the
British were taking over and the hill
people who are now called the nagas they
always had this close Allegiance and
alliance with the with the mateys with
the with the manipuri King overall they
have been the same people historically
so the the so-called nagas were now
called nagas they would conduct raids on
British positions and you know they
would harass the British you know and
things like that and this was in support
of the manipuri king so the British
wanted to create to drive a wedge in
this uh entire uh Arrangement so they
brought in these Outsiders these uh
these tribes people who were not Burmese
but who were in Burmese territory they
started settling them in Manipur
they started by settling them in the
South the southern regions of Manipur
you know south of Empire and all that
these were all Naga territories there
were lots of Hill people who are now
called nagas who lived in all these
regions south of imphal more south of
Etc
these uh tribals these Burmese Nationals
tribals they were settled here and
slowly over a few decades they brutally
and violently ethnically cleansed the
nagas from these parts of Manipur
so
the point of doing this was to create
instability and trouble and not allow
the nagas to be at peace so that they
can fight the British and also to create
problems for the methods and the
manipuri King it's that's the classic
trouble making approach the British have
always employed across the world
so that's why the British made the
manipuri king settle Burmese Nationals
in Manipur uh how many were settled when
did this happen let's take a look at
that
uh
let us go here
so this uh
one second not this one let me check
okay here we are so this I think it
began sometime in the late 19th century
it speaks about this is a snippet of a
book it says in January in February 1872
uh There Were Expeditions and all that
the captives uh
uh all that stuff
the whole of the above have been settled
by the Maharaja in the tangjing range of
hills and Valley Southwest of moirang so
these are all you know
some what we call cookies now
see Kong cookies and all that
uh so yeah they say that the Maharaja
did this but it was done at the behest
of the British so that's how it happened
it is the classic divide and Rule
strategy it create trouble for the
natives by settling Outsiders who are
inimical to you who don't respect and
value your culture I want to grab land
that's what the British did to create
trouble in Manipur so that they could
rule by creating trouble dividing them
everybody making everybody fight each
other so that they could exploit that
situation that's why the British did
that
I bet he doesn't even know how the term
cookie originated like I said the term
cookie originates from the word
the British brought in these uh tribal
tribes people from chin state in Burma
settle them in Manipur uh their their
job was to be Porters and laborers and
they were called cool coolies eventually
that morphed into the term cookies
so these foreign Outsiders Who were
settled by the British in the 19th
century in Manipur were originally
called kulis by them but then that term
morphed into the word that we use now
cookie
next
uh two questions two two comments 22 400
square kilometers never had formed
foreign Burmese tribes before the Advent
of the British and someone responds your
total land area was 700 square
kilometers will always be 700 square
kilometers
so the first so the first uh
this one here this the first line is by
clearly somebody who's a methane and the
second one is by somebody who is a
cookie and who claims that methods
always were residing in the imphal
valley region 700 square kilometers once
again let's go and
see the map
once again let's go and see the map uh
the imfal valley region is roughly 700
square kilometers and the cookies claim
the methias always lived there and
everything else is either Naga or cookie
territory mainly cook it already that is
the claim the cookies have been making
off late and that's what this comment is
about right so let's see how how true
this is let's see the veracity let's
examine the veracity of this claim
so this is a book that was written in
1873.
by somebody called R Brown clearly a
British occupier
it says native state of Manipur the hill
territory under its rule so it clearly
says that the hill territory is under
the rule of the state of Manipur or the
kingdom of Manipur and we know who are
the rulers so once again that that makes
it very clear now
uh let's get into this
so
so this is written in in 18
what let's see once again
1873. so this is well after the British
started settling Outsiders into Manipur
and the British by the time have had
started re-engineering the boundaries
and the map of Manipur so let's see what
it says here the territory which
constitutes a native state of Manipur
consists of a large extent of Hill
territory and the proper value of
Manipur
uh it gives you the latitudes and
longitudes 24 30 2560 and longitude 93
10 94 60
uh
okay so the northern boundaries of
Manipur are the angami country which is
uh
currently nagaland and the hills of The
Valleys of Assam the South the boundary
is undefined and so on but on the
country inhabited by various types of
Volusia cookies which is the chin chin
territory of present-day Burma
so if you look at the the latitude and
longitudes that this person has given
any if you superposed that on a map you
will see
you will see this
the the darker colored region in the map
on the map is what this person has
stated obviously it will not be exactly
square or rectangular but you get the
point so that actually
includes the present-day nagaland
capital of kohima in the city of dimapur
as well
and this is another different way of
representing that this is what the guy
claims was the roughly the boundaries of
Manipur in 1873 excuse me
so clearly and you know there was
something called uh there was something
called Cabo Valley
so the Cabo Valley was part of the
Manipur Kingdom it's now part of Burma
because our great magnificent prime
minister SRI jawaharlal nehruji gave it
away as if it was in her own personal
property to give to Burma right so the
Cabo Valley was part of the Manipur
Kingdom
and it was uh given away it was given on
lease by the British to Burma
okay let's see so this is the kingdom of
Burma you can see the Cabo Valley was
part of Manipur this over here is the
Cabo Valley
uh now let's see so this is the Kabob
Ali on the map
and this is the agreement
it is the intention of the Supreme
government to Grant a monthly stipend of
500 Rupees to the Raja of Manipur to
commence on the ninth day of January
1834 the date at which the transfer of
Cabo took place as shown in the
agreement and so on so the Burmese would
give the manipuri king Maharaja Raja a
payment a monthly stipend a monthly
payment in exchange for the valley which
would be on lease to Burma it doesn't
become part of Burmese territory right
and this is uh for the details of that
you can check it out you can freeze the
screen pause the screen and and take a
look at this right I'm gonna take it off
the screen now if you want to see the
the Cabo Valley I can show it to you on
the map itself
uh
so once again we go back to the map and
we search for combo Valley which is near
Murray
yes so this is the Cabo Valley as you
can see it's near more in TAMU and it's
slightly smaller than the imfal valley
but it's a significant region so all of
this was part of the kingdom of Manipur
you had methes living in all these
places you know you cannot keep on
distorting History to base to to suit
your agendas and all that
uh so it's quite clear it's evidently
clear from the British records
themselves the how large the kingdom of
Manipur was how large the territories
under its domain were
it's very clear that the chin people the
so-called cookies came from chin State
they were not manipuris they were never
in Manipur is the British who settled
them there I think it's very clear if
you examine just a few historical
records which are all available in the
public domain so I would encourage
everybody to look into this so these
claims that your total area was 700
square kilometers are laughable they are
visible they are asinine and they are
complete propaganda and fiction
the cookies are not manipuris they are
not they have never been Indians they
were settled by the British as
troublemakers in the late 19th century
so so that's that's the deal okay
says the cookies are original settlers
of Manipur just as mateys and Naga so
that's that's complete fiction like I
have just demonstrated uh that obviously
is is what these people claim now let's
let's
if these people claim that they are the
original settlers of Manipur so this
lady is using the word settlers
settlers
the meetings have been around for three
and a half thousand years they're not
settlers and so the same goes for the
nagas the cookies are settlers who are
settled artificially as a demographic
re-engineering project by the British in
Manipur in the late 19th century and
even
in the 20th century the cookies were
always regarded by the government of
India's refugees even though the
government of India was was was settling
them in Manipur for for some reason you
know what the government of India after
1947 was absolutely clueless about the
far East of India they had no
understanding of the history the culture
the demographics anything absolutely
clueless they did everything remote
control everything from Delhi the
nehruvian government and they simply
continued the British policies
in Manipur and in the Northeast
so they kept on settling
these Outsiders these foreigners in
India let me show you the evidence you
will say where's the evidence where is
the proof well please please don't mind
me showing you some evidence of that
this is June six or eight whatever it is
1968.
it is uh
under secretary Rehabilitation
Rehabilitation blah blah Deputy
Commissioner Manipur that's where the
letter comes from please refer to my
letter number whatever dated the 6th of
April 1968 copy enclosed for ready
reference and expedite your report
regarding resettlement of cookie
refugees from Burma so in 1968 also the
government of India was very clear that
these cookies were refugees from Burma
and I don't know why we were settling
them in in Manipur and in India why
why is India goddamn dharamshala that
anybody can come can be settled don't we
have any standards isn't India supposed
to be a sacred lands for land for
Indians only
so this is what the government did in
1968 they had been doing this since 1949
since Manipur became a part of India
first the nairobian regime and then
subsequent regimes
after Independence the nairobian regime
started issuing missionary visas
missionary visas come convert our people
to your wonderful foreign religion and
it was mainly American missionaries who
started flocking to the Far East of
India into Manipur into nagaland into
mizoram and they succeeded wildly
mizoram was more than 90 question by
around 1950. that's how rapid the
demographic engineering was and nagaland
took about until the 1980s to become 90
Christian
so you can see that the government of
India refers to these cookies is
refugees from Burma
so they are not indians they are cookie
refugees from Burma want to see more
here we go once again this is from 1968.
once again it says
it says this office is not in a position
to give comments regarding the legality
of the entry of a large number of cookie
tribal refugees from Burma
whether these refugees are to be
accepted in this country is a decision
of policy for the government to consider
some refugees have settled in the
vicinity of konkan Tana Village in ukrul
and this land is being claimed by the
neighboring Villages so you could see
the roots of the problem the neighboring
Villages were saying This Is Our Land
but the government of India was settling
this foreign cookie alien refugees in
India you see it was this was happening
in 1968 itself this problem the roots go
go back to to the British occupation of
Manipur late second half of a 19th
century and even more
in the 20th century in the roots are the
policies of the Indian government in the
after Independence ridiculous policies
settling cookie aliens in
Indian soil Indian Territory and you can
see at that time itself the various
local Villages were saying This Is Our
Land how can you give it to these people
so you know it's a This Disaster you can
see the disaster in the making over here
from these letters the disaster in the
making right here 1968 you can see the
roots of the disaster
which we are which we are currently
witnessing in Manipur right now
foreigners being settled in India
claiming Indian Territory as their own
and that just continued on and on and on
here's something more recent
there was a coup in Burma in 2021 the
Burmese junta the Burmese the the
Burmese military took back power from
aung San Jose's government
and uh there's a civil war going on in
Burma and it's displayed displaced one
million eight hundred and twenty seven
thousand people since February 21 out of
which 53 000 officially
from Kent State
have entered India's northeast states of
mizoram and Manipur who allowed these
foreigners to enter India for what
purpose
how did the government of India make the
choice the decision of allowing these
refugees into India
is that our problem
is that India's problem
I just don't understand these goddamn
policies which we are still seeing today
we are still seeing these policies today
let's see further and see it says 53 000
individuals cookies have entered
is refugees
uh in the last since February 21 that's
an official figure the actual figure as
we all know is going to be a multiple of
that like five times ten times of that
okay
this is a press release from 24th July
2023. so on 23rd of July 23 705
cookies crossed into the across the
India India Myanmar border and entered
Manipur chandel district and all the
specific details of how many males how
many females how many children which
area how many everything is given in
great detail which means that they did
not enter quietly or or surreptitiously
they they their entry was was was
monitored and the number of men children
Etc women children were was all noted
down and recorded
which means the security forces who are
guarding the borders allowed this to
happen
and recorded every single individual
and the government of Manipur said has
given a show cause notice why did you
allow this to happen and send them back
but I'm sure they've not been sent back
here we have some more illegal it says
very clearly illegal immigrants all
these cookies are illegal immigrants
please understand this they are not
indians
so this this claim that these
individuals make that cookies are
original settlers of Manipur and that's
what the Indian media is is is is you
know amplifying
the Indian media
which is I I just don't understand the
Indian media is amplifying all this
nonsense so so that's the deal these
cookies are foreign refugees illegal
infiltrators I think I have demonstrated
it very clearly through all these
documents the cookies aren't Indians
they have never been Indians they have
no Affinity with Indian culture they
have nothing in common with the people
of India the people of the Far East of
India the metis and the nagas nothing in
common with them but they want their
territory
that's what's happening the cookies
they're foreigners aliens illegal aliens
please understand this
okay next question
says okay thank you uh what are the best
measures to curb the foreign
interference to curtail the local
insurgences in India I mean I'm sure you
mean the Far East of India to understand
what we can do to curtail all this
nonsense we have to understand the
origins of these insurgencies
okay so after 1947 1949 1949 Manipur
joins the union of India after that the
government of India like I said adopted
the same policies that the British
adopted they said that if our British
Masters were doing something it should
have it must have been the right thing
so let's continue the same policies so
they completely isolated the Far East of
India from the rest of India let's go go
back to the map so that you understand
what's happening uh
so the nehruvian regime it starts with
Mr nehru the great man himself yeah what
he did was he completely isolated and
cut off the Far East of India Assam
onwards completely isolated this region
from the rest of India there was there
were no there was no new infrastructure
that was constructed very few roads were
constructed no new Railways even today
we hardly have any Railways in the Far
East of India no airports no connections
no hospitals no schools nothing no jobs
no progress no development and then you
had this Inner Line permit system which
means that if even if you lived in India
and you wanted to visit this part of
India you would need a special
permission for which you would have to
answer all kinds of questions and they
could deny it to you so that
marginalized the Far East of India
completely isolated it completely uh you
know
first of all the the the the original
kingdoms had been destroyed the princely
states had their power was taken away uh
and then this new governance system the
nehruvian government system was imposed
which was a disaster
so the people over here they felt
neglected they felt that they would be
given a very cruel stepmotherly
treatment there was no development
nobody could get jobs nobody could earn
money the only choice you had was either
you you become a drug addict because the
Golden Triangle is right next door the
drug popular producing region or you you
become a terrorist an insurgent and you
fight for independence
so this
caused a sudden explosion spontaneous
explosion of insurgencies separatist
incidences in all the states of the Far
East of India whether it is Assam
whether it's nagaland whether it's
Manipur whether it's mizoram everywhere
every state erupted in insurgencies and
everybody say there were multiple in
certain groups so in mizoram you had the
misos you know and that incidency went
so became so bad that a former prime
minister Mrs Gandhi Indira Gandhi she
had to take the incredible step of
asking the Indian Air Force to bomb the
capital city of isil and other other
places
that's how bad the meso incidency had
become right in in Assam you had the
Bodo the Bodo thing and all nagaland you
had various Insurgent groups in Manipur
you had Naga insurgents incidents and so
on imagine imagine this try to
comprehend this
try to comprehend this the methods
in the 19 in the 20th century were all
Hindus
today lots of them have converted
Christianity sadly
in the 20th century the Mathes were all
Hindus and they were fighting they had
in certain groups who were fighting to
separate Manipur from India imagine
Hindus being treated so badly they want
to separate from India can you imagine
that can you comprehend that it tells
you the status of Hindus in India
that gives you a very good idea of how
Hindus are treated in India Hindus did
not want to be a part of India that was
a situation
horrible absolutely horrible so that's
why you had all these insurgencies in
the Far East of India because of the
absolutely horrible cruel
marginalization and step motherly
treatment given by the government of
India
to this entire enormous region right so
that's why you had insurgencies and then
you obviously had the christianization
Mr nehru you know gave a red carpet
welcome to hordes of American Christian
missionaries to convert all the people
you know entire populations entire
tribes entire States nagaland and
mizoram especially megali also you have
so much of that now they are trying to
convert arunachal Pradesh as well so you
know I have absolutely nothing against
somebody choosing a new spiritual path a
new religious path let's say you are
tired of your religion you feel that
it's not helping you spiritually and you
want to try something different it's
your choice go ahead try any religion
you want right Christianity try try
Baha'i whatever it is try the old
Egyptian religion try anything you want
it's your choice you have the right to
do that I have nothing against that I
have nothing against any religion
but I have
a strong issue with the neo-colonial
practice of artificially re-engineering
the religious demographics of of regions
on a mass industrial scale
this is nothing but neocolonialization
and this has political motives
so that is the problem and that's what
Mr nehru facilitated in the Northeast so
today what you find is that there are
large populations who have completely
lost touch with their ancestral culture
of their roots and they no longer see
themselves
as some so as people who have any
Affinity with India and that is a huge
issue
so you're finding this issue everywhere
in very large Paths of the Far East of
India so these are the issues so to
curtail the local insurgences in these
regions you have to address the root
causes right
uh yeah so that's the thing
okay little prince 7144 says
irony of mateys are in favor of cookies
during okay
he or she is claiming that methes were
in favor of cookies during the cookie
nagar clashes of 1993 and supported the
policy of divided rule by parting mostly
Naga inhabited districts in the Hills
today's methods are facing the
consequences of their blunder decision
and short-sightedness till today many
nagas are refugees in their own land
occupied by cookies
no government is interested or initiated
to result to resettle those Naga
Villages you know this is the perception
the media has created that the method is
where Pro cookie
here's what happened in the 1990s there
were this terrible Naga cookie clashes
the cookies were encroaching into more
and more into Naga territory the hill
territory and they were taking over
their lands
So eventually the Naga said enough is
enough and they went they pushed back
violently very violently there was this
ramp this this horrible clashes riots
and the nagas went after the cookies
with the Vengeance okay I don't even
want to go into how what they did the
nagas went after the cookies
so this cookie operations the cookie
aggressors were certainly on the back
foot and they were being you know hunted
down by the nagas in certain regions in
certain parts of Manipur
and the media has created the impression
that the Mathis were in favor of the
cookies the methods
but not in favor of the cookies or
anybody they they tried to intervene and
calm the situation down
and whoever was being affected they kind
of you know gave them shelter for some
time and that sort of thing the maidens
did not take the side of the cookies and
against the nagas it was not that sort
of thing but I am sure that's the The
Narrative that has been created now and
I'm sure lots of people believe that the
myth is just tried to play Peacemaker
stop fighting that sort of thing and
yeah today the pressure has been created
that the methes took the side of the
cookies which they did not
uh
yeah it is true that nagas today are
refugees in their own land the same as
Mathis what's happened in Mathews it
first happened to the nagas
right the entirety of Southern Manipur
okay the southern part of Manipur all of
it south of Suraj
this entire region was the Abode of the
Hill people who are now called the nagas
there was not a single Burmese
individual there but now you have
Burmese everywhere these cookies these
were all Naga territories the nagas were
ethnically cleansed brutally and
violently from these regions in certain
tribal groups like The paite and the
hamar and the Combs were allowed to
continue existing on the condition that
they start identifying as cookies
so you will find that the pyth is in the
Hamas and various the announce these
tribes tribal groups they are now
classified as cookies they were never
cookies
they are not cookies but today that
classified is that so the the trade-off
was that we will allow you to
survive we will not kill you all but you
have to identify yourself as cookies
that's what the cookies did
so yes there are so many nagas who have
lost their lands their refugees in their
own land the same that's happening to
the mateys the government yeah what can
I say all the Naga Villages are gone in
the past couple of decades God knows how
many lacks of cookies have entered
Manipur many of them enter through
mizoram and they are given access
you know they are transported across
mizoram and then settled in Manipur
that's what's happening and the entire
border is open it's a very hilly
forested region it's very difficult to
to you know uh to fence it but I think
that's something that needs to happen
so uh yeah to answer this question or
this comment the methods were not in
favor of the cookies they were simply
trying to calm things down to play
peacemakers not favoring one side or
another
uh but yes they were kind of
you could say
kind
you know to the cookies and now they're
being paid back by the cookies for being
kind to them by you know that sort of
thing
um
so understand the methods did not take
these the side opposite of the nagas
they did not stop the nagas or prevent
or fight the nagas or impede the nagas
in whatever they were doing they simply
tried to calm things down and maybe help
out whoever was affected and today this
this impression has been created
okay
says how can we deal with the aliens who
have been filtered from Myanmar and who
are getting into politics in the
Academia academic Circles of India and
Akil says all are making the Mathis
villains who are Hindus who don't have
any reservations right you know so what
happens lacks of these cookies they
infiltrate into into India into Manipur
uh either from the chin State directly
or via mizoram that's what's the meaning
manipuri media has been reporting for a
long time
they are foreigners they come into
Manipur they settle down they create new
Villages you know in the past few years
more than a thousand new Villages have
appeared in Manipur uh let's go back to
the map
you will not see these villages
on the map of Manipur but if you see if
you go to Google Earth and you see the
satellite images you will see
at least a Thousand Villages that have
cropped up in recent times that are not
registered and that they do not appear
on the map so that's an there's an
incredibly huge influx of illegal
foreign Burmese Nationals into Manipur
it's always Manipur it's not mizoram the
misos are not settling any cookie in
mizoram they are being told to go and
settle Manipur you see it's interesting
uh so when once these people settle down
in say Manipur they automatically are
you know what happens first of all they
acquire Indian documentation
let me show you evidence of that
they acquire Indian documentation
so let me give you
ah here we are
okay
so these guys once they reach India they
acquire other cards
other cards are being essentially sold
for 8 000 rupees a piece in mizoram
Myanmar refugees in mizoram found with
forged government documents the same
thing is happening with illegal
Bangladesh the same thing is happening
with illegal rohingyas they all get get
genuine aadhar cards once you have
another card you can get a passport and
that's it
that's it you're a citizen so that's how
easy it is 8 000 bucks and you get
another card and I assure you it's not
going to be a fake aadhar card
so that's what happens so once they get
another card and then then they are
Indian Nationals
even though the other card is not
official proof of nationality but the
passport is and you can get a passport
on the base of another card so what
nonsense is this the other the other
other documentation is not enough for
nationality
you can get a passport on the base of
that that is proof of rationality so
that's how easy it is for these Burmese
illegal infiltrators to get Indian
documentations once this happens they
are classified as schedule tribes so
they get all kinds of benefits and perks
that the Mathis don't get they get the
reservations in schools and colleges and
universities they get financial benefits
they get reservations in government jobs
in you know academic jobs they get they
become professors they become academics
they become IIs officers they become IPS
officers when the entire Manipur uh this
entire issue started in the beginning of
May the DGP of Manipur was a cookie
you see uh
so that's what's happening
these guys automatically the moment they
settle down in India and in a week or
two or whatever time it takes to get
other card and then maybe a passport or
whatever else then they immediately get
all kinds of benefits of that ordinary
Indian citizens don't get
the myth is our general category
like all other Hindus or like most other
Hindus I I don't know I let me take that
back the myth is a general category they
are not SC or St or whatever so they get
no benefits No Reservations in their own
land in their own State they are
marginalized they are confined to six
percent of the territory by Indian law
yeah and then these Outsiders are
foreigners who come in they came in two
weeks ago get all kinds of benefits
that's what happens and there are
professors
in certain universities in India who
were born in Burma it's documented
there are certain people who have served
as MPS in Burma's Parliament who are now
Indian Nationals
that's the kind of joke that India has
become today
no standards at all
uh so uh yeah so they get into politics
they become politicians they become
professors they become police officers
they become IIs officers they become
lawyers they become Advocates and
because it's so they get so many
benefits from you know
so it's easy for them to do all this and
they are start occupying all the
positions of power just a few years
after they enter India illegally this is
what India is doing to its own people
and it's it's a disaster so how can we
deal with this the government has to
crack down on this nonsense what needs
to happen is an NRC to identify all the
foreigners that NRC has to be done
properly not on the basis of other cards
which are all fake anybody can get
another card for eight thousand bucks so
you can't make that the basis of your
National register of citizens do you
have another car or not that's not
enough
you have to prove
your the you have to prove that your
ancestors were in India before a certain
cut of date that's what you have to
prove if you can't prove it and you
can't force the methods to do this you
have to apply this only to The Outsiders
so yeah that could be a way of dealing
with this but will the government do it
to what extent will be will they do it I
don't know
Holy crom says uh
could you please shed some light on the
soo and explain what the government of
India is not taking decisive action to
crush the foreign Invaders despite
having extensive evidence
so what is this Soo that's what we want
to see right the suspension of
operations agreement
uh do I have something to deal with that
okay so the suspension of operations
agreement is something that that came
into effect into in 2008.
the then government of India entered
into this agreement with the cookie
insurgents the cookie terrorists that
government of India was led by the great
man Bohan Singh ji As We Know
so that government uh entered into this
agreement with the cookie terrorists in
this as part of this agreement
the cookie terrorists were allowed to
keep their weapons all their weapons
they were made to register the number of
terrorists that they have they were
allowed to keep operating their
terrorist camps
with weapons with their flags with their
fake fictitious Nations Flag
um and
they were the the local paramilitary
forces like the Assam rifles were told
to monitor the the activities
on a routine basis so that established
good relations within the Assam rifles
and the cookie terrorists
that's what is being said allegedly uh
so that was the suspension of operations
agreement when it came to the methane
Insurgent groups they were all disarmed
they were all required to put down their
weapons and they were totally disarmed
some of these so-called in certain
groups they still operate maybe across
the border in Burma or somewhere but
they don't have any public support at
all the methane people the manipuri
people want peace they want development
that's what they've always wanted
so the methods were disarmed the cookies
were allowed to keep their weapons their
sophisticated weapons from where they
got all that yeah
and they were allowed to keep their
terrorist caps let's take a look at the
location
of these terrorist caps shall we take a
look
these were these cookie terrorist camps
they ring fence the imphal valet the
city of imphal
you you must have heard of the Chinese
string of pearls strategy to encircle
India
well see the methods the original people
of Manipur are forced by Indian law to
only live in the imfa valley they're not
allowed access to the rest of their
ancestral territories and this small
tiny territory where they are they are
forced to be confined to there is now
ring fenced by these cookie terrorist
caps
this is the suspension of operations
agreement of India
excuse me
and it is it is alleged that the cookies
the terrorists they they are not uh you
know upholding the terms of the
suspension of operations agreement and
uh more terrorists are coming in from
the chin state from across Burma and so
on so that essentially is the suspension
of operations agreement the government
of India the man bones and government
gave special preferential uh treatment
and status to the cookie terrorists
the cookie insurgents they disarm the
methods why why give preference and
special treatment to foreign aliens
illegal infiltrators
I just don't get it why were they not
disarmed like everybody else
why were they allowed to continue on and
why were they allowed to ring fence the
capital city like that
I just don't understand so that's what
the soo is the suspension of operations
agreement it's and
and another clause in the soo
was that each cookie terrorist who is
registered will be given a stipend of
six thousand rupees per month at Indian
taxpayer expense so every year when you
pay taxes some of it goes
into the pockets of the koki terrorists
great privilege for all of all of us to
be funding the cookie terrorists
so the question is why does why is the
government of India not taking decisive
action to crush the foreign Invaders
despite having extensive evidence we
have all the evidence of these people in
their terrorist activities and what
they're doing now as I have demonstrated
this problem started more than a century
ago the roots of the problem are in the
second half of the 19th century the
whole of the 20th century post
Independence we made it even worse our
government right so that's where the pro
that's how the problem has been made to
exist that's how the problem was created
now unfortunately it is Mr Mr Narendra
modi's job to fix everything
he has inherited this enormous issues
and he is required to
solve all the problems
and if you can't solve them in a few
months or a few years then he's the bad
guy right that's see people don't have
patience
and that's why people are upset uh the
question is why is India not taking
decisive action the government knows
what the cookies are doing
the thing is
There is almost no distinction today
between the kooky terrorists and regular
infiltrators who are living in The
Villages the terrorists also have
families in The Villages I am sure there
are weapons in The Villages automatic
weapons and all that in the Villages so
if you want to actually disarm the
cookies you'll have to go not only only
the to the terrorist camps but also into
the villages and that's gonna be
essentially you'll have to take action
against civilians if they're going to
fight back
and then you're gonna have to shoot at
civilians which you can't
I mean you can but then because they're
terrorists but then the whole world is
waiting for this to happen
the whole world is waiting for something
like this to happen so that they can
blame India for human rights violation
and fascism and operation of minorities
and blah blah blah
so that is the Dilemma India is
currently in it will take time to solve
this problem unfortunately until then
the wonderful people of Manipur have to
suffer
so that is the deal that's what's
happening
okay next
says how can we deal with illegal
influxes from Burma
first thing is to
uh
you know fence the Border
which is a very difficult and lengthy
time consuming task we will have to
fence the Border not only of Manipur and
Burma but also mizoram and Burma and
will the Miso people be open to fencing
the Border
and will the cookies allow fencing the
Border because they control all the
Border areas
but it has to be done if we want to stop
the illegal influx
you know ideally we we don't want to
have a fenced border with Burma
the Burmese people are very nice people
they are the same culture as us in 1935
the people of Burma voted to not
separate from India but the British
still separated born of India
it's only the cookies
who are a problem they are fighting a
war against the Burmese Nation too a
secessionist separatist War
so the only solution right now
is to fence the border with Burma which
is going to be an enormous Endeavor it's
going to take years
that's the or the other thing is you
cooperate with the Burmese government
to uh let's say subdue the terrorist
activities of the cookies in chin State
because the entire problem is coming
from chin state in Burma
chin state which I just showed you let's
go again chain State chain
State Myanmar
so this shaded region is the homeland of
the cookies uh you know 500 years ago
they were not even here the cookies
originally came from somewhere in yudan
China and they settled in this region
and they have been fighting the Burmese
ever since
so yeah
so either we fence the entire border
which I would say is a kind of
undesirable we would like to have
actually an open border with Burma Burma
is not a hostile country it's a friendly
country
um
so if you want to keep an open border
you have to uh subdue the separatist
terrorist Insurgency in Chen State maybe
we can join hands with the Burmese
government to do that or not otherwise
we fence the border which will take
years but yeah these are the two
solutions to stop the illegal influx
from Burma
next question
Margaret says this is a Hindu Christian
conflict uh peaceful Naga says why the
nagas and 30 other different fellow
tribals and Christian communities
Manipur are not supporting the cookies
and there's some some YouTube link
listen
Margaret this is not a Hindu Christian
conflict that is a lie there is a
misrepresentation
this Naga person himself or herself is
saying the nagas and other Christian
communities are not supporting cookies
let's take a look at the history of the
cookies in India
between 1917 and 1919 the the cookies
fought the kabui
tribal group in the thankful tribal
group I think both are now classified as
nagas the kabui may not be classified as
nagas perhaps the tankos are definitely
nagas so the cookies for the tangles at
that time the bankers were still
polytheists okay they were not
christianized yet in 1917 1990.
between 1959 and 1960 the cookies fought
a civil war with the hamar tribal group
let's take a look at the hamar tribal
group shall we
I'm gonna put a Wikipedia page on the
screen statutory warning you cannot
trust Wikipedia for everything but I'm
just putting it for ease of information
if you look at this people is a cookie
ethnic group living in Northeast instead
of manipuram that's what it says let's
go to the history shall we the history
of this Wikipedia page let's see 500
revisions okay it said that the Mars are
a cookie ethnic group now let's see a
revision from let's say uh
let's say
December 2022
in December it said are one of the
ethnic peoples of the cookie chin miso
group
now if you go back further
let's say to let's say December 2022
okay same thing now you go back further
let's go to let's say September 2022
it says or an ethnic miso group so in
September 22 there were misos in
December there were cookies and today
they are simply cookies you see how
these people are manipulating the
information on Wikipedia to suit their
agendas and objectives okay
have never been cookies they were one of
the Hill tribes of Manipur
and the cookies fought a civil war with
them in 1959 1960 they almost eliminated
eliminated them and then forced them to
start considering themselves cookies so
I start identifying themselves as
cookies the same thing happened with the
anau that's another group then you had
the Naga cookie clashes in the or in the
early to mid 90s 92 to 95 1992 to 1995
roughly at that time the nagas were all
Christians they had been converted to
Christianity
and the cookies were also Christians so
how come there was the civil war between
the nagas and the cookies in the in the
1990s both were Christian groups so
where is this the a Hindu Christian
conflict what we are saying today is a
continuation of all these things it's
not a new conflict that has started
today right and then in the you had the
various other conflicts the cookies for
the nagas the cookies the cook when I'm
talking about the cookies I'm talking
about the thado which is the major
tribal group of the cookies they fought
the nagas they fought the Hamas they
fought the pythas were also Christians
now they fought the dimasas who in 2003
I believe
in 2003 2004 they fought the carbies in
Assam and now they are fighting the
methods and they are also fighting a
Civil War in Insurgency terrorist
Insurgency in Bangladesh they're also
fighting a terrorist Insurgency in
Myanmar they are fighting everybody
it's not a religious conflict
do not portray this as a Hindu Christian
conflict or any such thing there is
nothing religious about this it's an
expansionist rapacious group of people
tribes people who came from Hunan
originally who are now trying to create
an imaginary country
independent country imaginary in this
entire region that's what it is the
nagas who are Christians do not support
the cookies the nagas are fought the
cookies in the past this is not this has
nothing to do with religion and don't
portray this as a Hindu Christian
conflict which is complete which is a
complete misrepresentation of what's
Happening
next question
says has the media shown the truth about
what the cookies want can you explain
what exactly is cookie land they are
claiming many states of far east as
cookie land also why is the media not
showing what's happening to the methods
why only one side of the story is being
shown that's what the Indian media does
always if you see the reporting in the
Ukraine war they will only show
reporting from the Western perspective
and from Ukrainian soil there were two
or three Indian channels that sent
journalists to cover the war they all
cover covered the conflict from the
Ukrainian side of the conflict in
Ukrainian territory they should have
sent two journalists to Ukraine and two
into Russia and cover the things from
both sides so that we understand what's
really happening properly but no we're
only show one side of the picture this
is what the Indian media always does
and obviously there are agendas behind
this
Hindus and the indigenous people have to
be shown as the oppressors the evil
majoritarian oppressors despite the myth
is now being a micro minority in their
own you know ancestral land so the media
doesn't want to show you what's
happening to the metis they are always
portraying the methods as the aggressors
in the cookies as the victims that's
that's what they're showing they're
showing only one side of the story
because they are gender driven and uh I
suppose they have foreign funding in
foreign Masters to who's whose agenda
they have to uh you know cover
okay what is the what is Cookie Land
Cookie Land is an imaginary Nation it is
a
it is a nation that doesn't exist it is
a nation that will never exist it's a
fictitious fake imaginary Nation uh let
me show you what kind of cookie land
they want okay they want to cut off
India
from the Far East
from from from Southeast Asia so here is
one example of what Google this is a
this is a tweet from 2019 okay
join me in the fight for the Christ and
cookie land to be a Christian country it
lies in the middle of Indo Burma Indo
Bangladesh it is recorded as cookie
country in linguistic survey whatever
whatever and he has tagged Donald Trump
and God knows who else so if you can see
the Shaded regions of this map it will
tell you that they want to take over
very large parts of India's Far East and
cut off India's access
to Southeast Asia so today you will find
let's go to the map okay today you will
find that India's access to almost the
entire world has been cut off
Pakistan and Pakistan occupied Kashmir
cut off India's access to Central Asia
and Europe
Chinese occupied Tibet cuts off India's
access to Northern Asia
and China
and then what we have left is southeast
Asia right but we have never developed
the infrastructure and the roads in the
railways to access southeast Asia even
though we have uh borders with Burma and
through which we can go into Thailand
into Vietnam Cambodia all the way to
Singapore we can go all the way to
Singapore by Road or by rail if we
construct the roads and Grill
and right now we are in the Indian
government is constructing a road the
Indo Burma Friendship Road which passes
through more
but more has now been ethnically
cleansed by the cookies there are no
mateys who survive there they have been
let's say eliminated uh there were lots
of tamils more than fifteen thousand
thousand tamils who are living in Moray
today there are maybe two three thousand
tamils left where did the rest go ask
the mate ask the cookies
so more which is a critical Border City
has now been taken over the cookies
and they want to take over the entire
border regions and create their
fictitious fake nation of cookie land
zalangam or whatever the hell they want
to call it yeah
so that is what cookie land is this is
one of the you know
one of the versions of their great
aspirations fight for the Christ and
cookie land a Christian country that
will cut off India's access to Southeast
Asia
here is another one
this is an even larger
piece of territory they don't they seek
to you know uh carve out of India and
Bangladesh
and Burma as well they want to take
territories from three nations India
Burma and Bangladesh and create a fake
fictitious Nation cookie land zalingam
whatever
here's another example of that as you
can see even larger
they have something called the zoomy
platform for Burma and India occupied
zoland you see over over here in India
they're saying no we only want a
separate Administration from money from
the mateys we cannot live with the
methods we want a separate
Administration a separate state but they
actually want a separate nation and they
call
these parts of India India occupied Zoo
land whatever on Earth that means
and they have a Twitter account called
cookie government Democratic Republic of
kukilan is a non-violent government of
the kuki nation formed for restoration
and sovereignty of cookie land it shall
be a Christian country Bangladesh India
and Myanmar
so this is their agenda this is what
they want their fictitious fake nation
of cookie land or zalingam or whatever
they call it a nation that does not
exist and a nation that will never exist
if you want a nation go fight somewhere
else not not an inch of Indian Territory
will be given to you let's make it very
clear about that
Earth
says do you believe that if cookies are
to be given separate Administration the
next step for them is to ask for an
independent Cookie Chinese country
think about it this way
uh we have something this this issue
that the great SRI jawaharlal nehruji
the great magnificent prime minister he
created this issue for us the Kashmir
issue right the Kashmir conflict he gave
away parts of Kashmir to Pakistan which
is Pakistan okay but Kashmir Pakistan
the region which has been given to China
that entire issue right and the
pakistanis said that Kashmir is ours
they have been saying this for a very
long time today they are in no position
to say it anymore because they are so
because India has gone so far ahead of
them but in the past they were like we
will take Kashmir Kashmir hamara and all
the nonsense and there were lots of
Indian politicians who were like oh give
it to them give Kashmir to Pakistan
let's solve the issue
you know if you give Kashmir to Pakistan
hypothetically
you know Manmohan Singh wanted to give
away to Pakistan
allegedly
the thing is if you hypothetically give
away Kashmir to Pakistan do you think
Pakistan will become India's friend no
Pakistan will not become India's friend
Pakistan sees India as the permanent
adversary permanent enemy The Nation to
be destroyed
you give them Kashmir you give them
anything else they will never be
satisfied until they destroy you
completely
right and you cannot give in to the
black male of violent people
you cannot give in to the blackmail of
the intolerant
of the ones who do not abide by the law
especially ones who are not Indian so
similarly if you give these cookies a
separate Administration so-called
they will not be satisfied with that
they are fighting for any for an
imaginary Nation called zalingam or
zoland or Cookie Land
they want to take parts of Burma parts
of India large parts of India huge parts
of India and parts of Bangladesh and
create this
fake fictitious Nation giving them
territory is going to only encourage
them to push further
you do not negotiate
with blackmailers and terrorists
you know not given to the intolerant
ones
you simply don't do that so yeah if you
give them separate Administration The
Next Step eventually in a few years will
be to ask for more and more and more
and in India they will say oh we want
separate Administration but when they go
to the U.S when they go to Washington
they are claiming that India is
oppressing us
they were demonstrating outside the
White House a couple of months ago and
they were saying that Narendra Modi
government is fascist and they are
oppressing us and all that so in India
they sing a certain tune outside India
they sing a very different tune
you cannot give in to their demands you
simply can't
okay
says how can we deal with public
cultivation by slash and burning or
slashing and burning of forest areas
Smileys 3 news says is this really a
fight between the maidens and the
cookies I think the conflict is
indirectly between the drug Mafia and
the central government what are the
chances of this
says is the ban on opium in Afghanistan
but the Taliban does it have some
relation with Manipur the West is
concerned about the ban on opium Taliban
and we see increase in opium farming in
East in Manipur Etc allegedly yeah we're
good questions
so when the Taliban were fighting the
U.S occupiers of Afghanistan and the
puppet government that the Americans had
put up in Kabul at that time the Taliban
needed money so they used to rely on
opium cultivation and selling the
produce wherever it is wherever you get
buyers and that's what brought them
money right
once the Taliban took over Afghanistan
the Americans gave away Afghanistan to
the Taliban
established the government and settle
down they shut down all the puppy
cultivation
because after all it's a bad thing it's
going to be bad for the people drugs are
evil drugs are bad the drugs destroy
lives
right so the Taliban are Pashto
nationalists and they shut down the
puppy cultivation more than 99 of the
puppy
plantations have been destroyed in
Afghanistan and the Americans were
unhappy with this there were editorials
in various American very
prominent American Publications
criticizing the Taliban for shutting
down public cultivation
and coincidentally while the poppy
cultivation was been shut down in
Afghanistan you had this upsurge in
popular cultivation in Manipur
in large parts of Manipur
so much of this not all not all but much
of it is being done by the cookie
infiltrators
what they do is they take over large
parts of Manipur they you know they
destroy forests huge amounts of
protected
forests are destroyed cut down slash and
burn and then the plant poppy is there
and you know the Golden Triangle the
tri-junction of Laos Laos Burma and
Thailand which has historically been a
hotbed of drug cultivation especially
poppy opium and heroin heroin is
something you synthesize from opium
uh which comes from poppies so the
Golden Triangle is right next door and
obviously there are drug lords involved
in this
and much of the of the cultivation is
being done by the cookies right and
that's what they have been doing in
Burma as well now now the Burmese
government is cracking down on the
cookies because they're fighting the
Burmese government it says well we're
going there so now all of that has been
moved into much of that has been moved
into Manipur and then the Manipur
government was cracking down on this and
this is one of that's one of the
triggers that you know set up this what
what we could call Civil War Manipur now
on May the 3rd this year
so the methane cookie it's definitely a
fight between with the the cookies and
the methods the cookies are trying to
um ethnically the cleanse the methods
from even parts of the Valley now they
want to take our
essentially everything they want to
confine the maidis only to one city in
Fall everything else will take over
so it's not just cookies and methods
there are nagas to involve nagas are
also the victims the methods are
definitely the victims and the cookies
are the aggressors
and the the cookies much of the public
cultivation is being done by the cookies
it's a huge massive lucrative source of
income which allows them to buy
sophisticated weapons from God knows
where and so on right
so there are definitely drug laws
involved and all that there is
definitely Afghanistan angle the
Afghanistan public cultivation was
slammed Shut by the Taliban at the same
time somehow poppy cultivation there was
a there was this big upsurge in Manipur
clearly there seems to be some kind of
hidden connection what is the hidden
connection one wonders right
so how can we deal with public
cultivation by slashing and burning of
forest areas you have to shut down all
of these cultivations if necessary by
force it's still happening the cookies
Won't Give Up
you have to shut it down if they are
unwilling to give it up you have to put
them in jail you have to shut down
what's happening drugs are bad drugs
destroy lives we don't want drug
cultivation in India as simple as that
it has to happen but the government has
to show the political will to do this
eventually it will do that but I wonder
how long it will take
drumil Shah says from where does from
where do these cookie terrorists are
getting their modern weapons
and how much of a role does the church
and the U.S play in this genocide okay
let's talk about the cookie weapons and
all that right so
what you will see in so on social media
and all that is you will see this these
videos of cookies
with who are you know
who are firing at methi Villages from
hilltops like I showed they have ring
fenced in fall but they are present all
across the the other parts of Manipur as
well and whenever you have small methi
villages they are firing with automatic
weapons from the hilltops at the at the
villages so the mythies who live in
these areas are farmers and they are
unable to farm so all their crops will
be lost and then they will have to
depend on the central government for
assistance
because they're all the crops will be
lost this year
so where are these weapons coming from
you will see these guys this cookie
terrorists with very sophisticated
weapons very sophisticated weapons you
will see mortars you will see excuse me
drones that drop grenades the kind of
drones you see in the in the Ukraine
conflict kind of
and you will see very sophisticated
uh assault rifles and whatnot where are
they getting this from it's a very good
question right
so uh with the cookies clearly have a
lot of money from drug cultivation
so if you see Manipur you will see that
the northern part of Manipur if you if
you measure the distance from here
to let's say Yunnan province of China
it's less than 300 kilometers through
hilli through hilly terrain through
difficult hilly and forested terrain but
it's less than 300 kilometers the
Chinese have historically been very
willing and very happy to uh to help
separatists in various parts of India
the northeast of India far east of India
uh
they helped various separatists the
Bordeaux separatists the Naga
separatists the methods are produced
everybody especially the Naga
separatists the Chinese there are
pictures of the various separatist
leaders in the Great Wall of China and
all that that you can see on the
internet right
so one way of getting these
sophisticated weapons is definitely
through China and you will see some
chinese-made assault rifles and all that
the cookies have you will see that in
various social media posts and videos
so one possibility is China the Golden
Triangle is a trigunction of of Thailand
Myanmar and Laos was it which is this
region and obviously Southern Yunnan is
involved in that so this region where
you have so much drug running drug
production you will have a huge influx
it will be Awash with sophisticated
weapons because you need sophisticated
weapons to to safeguard your drug
operations right
so I'm sure some of some of that is
being transferred to to the cookies in
Manipur now and obviously Yunnan
obviously is nearby so uh from there
also you could be having this
the other possibility is Bangladesh but
Bangladesh the government is fighting
the cookies because they are trying to
separate uh you know carve out a piece
of territory from Bangladesh as well
so definitely not Bangladesh I I would
not think it would come from Bangladesh
most likely it would come from the
Yunnan region of China
how much role does the church in America
play in this genocide well you know we
don't have information
do they even play a role maybe may not
be but yeah
the church is more than a religious
organization it's a political
organization
it controls the politics
of
of these various states that are almost
completely christianized especially
mizoram and nagaland the cookies are
also all Christians so definitely we'll
have some church angle in there but how
much
is there we don't know so I can't really
comment more about that but yeah
next question
okay two questions Chain Gang Soldier
nit
I think half spot maybe needed to be put
in place again this time to covertly
clear out the trash and as passion 3
says wonder why not imposition of f spy
and Colin Army for a limited time US
Army Assam rifles and other special
forces like paramilitary forces are not
active due to lack of aspa of spa the
state government and Central have
totally failed to access the situation
and did not use etc etc etc a lot of
death destruction heinous crimes
especially against women and children
the methi are being blamed completely by
Christians media Christian nations
Christian ecosystem giving religious
color against them
as is always being done in India against
Hindus on the uh name of minorities okay
all that is fine the question is about
afspa the Armed Forces special power act
let's take a look at offspa
okay let's take a look at our spa
uh I'm gonna put a Wikipedia page on the
screen once again statute statutory
warning you cannot trust Wikipedia for
everything I'm just putting it briefly
when rapidly for reference cursory
reference so this is the page for apps
and first of all let's go to another
page
which is
this is from a government website the
Armed Forces special power act Powers
Act 1958 it starts by saying that
violence became a way of life in the
northeastern states of India well it was
the government of India that was
responsible for this happening yeah and
then they imposed the they created this
special powers ordinance or act in 1958
that gives extraordinary powers to the
Armed Forces to act in these Disturbed
areas and this is the entire thing you
can take a look at that now
the question is should we have offspine
Manipur by the way the answer is we
already have offspine Manipur let's come
down here this may not be entirely
accurate but it gives you a good idea of
where aspa is
so in Manipur all of these regions
already have offspa imphal East include
excluding like one to three police
stations in Fall West explo including
one two three four five six seven police
stations
all excluding one police station
jurisdiction
so three plus how many one two three
four five six seven three percent
fourteen apart from 14 police station
jurisdictions in Manipur everything else
is under half Spa
Armed Forces special power Act
everything in Manipur with the exception
of 14 police stations jurisdictions is
already under half Spa imphal the city
is not under half spa and there is no
violence in imphal
there's no violence in Fall there are
cookies who live in fun and they are
safe there is no violence against them
but the parts of Manipur where you have
this Rampage of violence they have
offspa
and by the way ashba was imposed in
Manipur in 1958. Manipur was declared a
disturbed state in 1958 and offspa was
removed finally from some parts of
Manipur in 2006. half a decade of offspr
in Manipur which did not solve any
problem
what did asper do
what did it do
and today the parts of Manipur like I
said where you don't have offspa are
peaceful
they're burning
so I don't think of spy is the solution
you see you see my point here I don't
think apps why is the solution I I I'm
sure can be kept where it already is but
those those regions are where you
already have all these disturbances
and this terrorism and after is doing
nothing to curb that
so the solution is not
maybe it's not office maybe something
else
see
okay this is a long question more is
part of the ACT East policy it's it's at
the heart of the Actis policy it now
completely controlled by the Myanmar
controlled cookie militants understand
that the cookie militants the cookie
terrorists are not controlled by the
Myanmar government they are fighting the
Myanmar government
this entire terrorism the cookie
terrorism Insurgency in Manipur it has
nothing to do with the government of
Myanmar the cookies are fighting Myanmar
the government they're also fighting the
methods and they're also finding
Bangladesh so it is completely incorrect
to blame the government of Myanmar for
what's happening they themselves are
trying to fight the cookies you see uh
okay continuing the government of India
has completely failed Manipur attacking
the crisis the center uh all that yeah
all right offspr is called cause and
told miseries in Manipur started
developing after our spouse is lifted
the valley areas after the May 3 riots
there's no violence inside the office in
Palm Valley region but there is
continuous terrorist activities
uh Unleashed by illegal cookie militants
who ironically live in the after areas
exactly exactly what I said wherever you
don't have a spell you have peace right
now and whenever you have you have
terrorism so that's the deal is not
going to prevent what's happening you
have asthma where the cookies are doing
whatever they're doing it's not stopping
them from doing what they're doing
it's not stopping them
um is at the heart of the ACT East
policy let's take a look at more more is
an extremely important uh strategically
located town for India it was supposed
to be India's gateway to Southeast Asia
foreign
to some extent
the methods have been totally eliminated
from from Moray in the past two months
only
and out of fifteen thousand thousand
tamils maybe two thousand or so may be
left in Murray this is what the cookies
have done the cookies have essentially
taken control of moray the government of
India I don't know if it even exists in
Murray anymore but our strategic Road
the Indo Burma Friendship Road it goes
through Moray and uh yeah so that's
that's a disaster for India as far as we
are concerned it's it's at the heart of
India's actually is at least policy
uh so in the future when India develops
finally after a million years Road and
rail links with southeast Asia excuse me
with Burma
Thailand Laos Cambodia Vietnam Malaysia
all the way to Singapore it will all
pass through Manipur it will all pass
through Moray Mori will be one of the
central uh you know it will be at the
heart of this active policy and right
now it's controlled by these foreign
illegal infiltrator alien terrorists
it's a disaster so this is completely
this I agree this is a failure of the
government of India this should not have
happened they should have seen this
coming but yeah here we are
what is the geopolitical angle in the
prison chaos in Manipur and Manipur
United says what is the current Manipur
crisis have to do with World geopolitics
including Myanmar Junta and
pro-democracy groups and Western forces
why is Indian defense not neutralizing
the chilled militants occupying Manipur
geopolitics is always at the heart of
the matter
in things like these so let's once again
take a look at the map
see
the U.S wants to use India to counter
balance China China is the big enemy for
the us right now the U.S doesn't want
India to become too powerful either
because then if once China is dealt with
India will be the big competitor so they
want to use India as a counterweight to
China but they don't want India to rise
too much so how do you prevent India
from rising too much by creating all
kinds of problems in India's periphery
so one example is that the Americans are
strongly against the current Bangladesh
government the Sheikh Hasina government
which they perceive as being too
strongly pro-india they don't want a
pro-india government in Bangladesh it is
none of that business but they are
trying to uh effect a regime change in
Bangladesh in the next election that's
what the Americans are trying to do
secondly Myanmar
uh the Americans have imposed a whole
host of sanctions on Myanmar after the
OMG Suki government was deposed in the
2021 coup by the Burmese military
uh and the Americans perceive Burma
Myanmar as becoming kind of pro-china
and they don't want that so they are
that's why they have imposed sanctions
but that actually has taken away all the
Leverage The Americans have on Burma now
the Burmese government is facing
terrorism and Insurgency from the
cookies in chin state
so if the Americans don't like the
Burmese government and if the cookies
are fighting the Burmese government it
makes sense for the Americans to like
and to support the cookies
you see that is the logic of strategy
that is simple that's a simple
mathematical thing
my enemy's enemy is my friend that sort
of thing the Americans are also trying
to create trouble in Thailand right so
uh if you remember in case you noticed
in 2020 2021 there were these
spontaneous pro-democracy protests in
Thailand you know Green haired purple
head pink head students were protesting
for democracy they were saying down with
the monarchy of Highland down with the
King down with the chakri dynasty down
with King Rama
that is something the Americans
obviously were doing this is the
standard color Revolution Playbook
apparently spontaneous protests emerge
out of nowhere and they also disappear
out of uh into nowhere
protests never happen spontaneously they
have to be coordinated you need
leadership behind that you need you need
coordination you need leadership you
need funding
and all that it never happens
spontaneously no political parties
appears spontaneously out of thin air so
the Americans clearly are behind the
Thai protests which happen in 20 20 21
and right now they were trying to uh you
know position in aspiring zelinski as
the prime minister of Thailand his name
is pita Lim
let's try and search for that gentleman
he's he's uh an aspiring zelenski pro-us
politician who the Americans were trying
to position and and install as the prime
minister of Thailand they have failed
okay so that's the kind of game the
Americans are known to be playing in
in our vicinity in India's neighborhood
so the Americans are involved in Burma
they they are opposed to the Burmese
government they are trying to uh effect
regime change in Bangladesh they are
trying to effect a regime change in
Thailand they are again supporting
Pakistan you know Pakistan is once again
a Visa of the U.S
and and so on so and so you will say
that India is essentially encircled by
by all these countries where the
Americans have something or the other
going on
uh so since the Americans are against
the Burmese government and since the
cookies are fighting the Burmese
government it makes sense that the
Americans are pro cooking and you will
see the U.S institute for peace and so
on
CE again U.S incident for peace U.S
institute for peace
okay let's put that on the screen that
the US Institute for peace so this is an
American Federal Government institution
tasked with promoting conflict
resolution and prevention worldwide
let's take a look at the Twitter
handle
so this is the Twitter handle
let's go to Media it won't allow me
to see
okay let's go back
and let's go to the website
Let's uh
uh balancing Balancing Act
so they have been writing about various
things NATO's Balancing Act
Burma's balancing actor time is running
out for India's balancing act on the
Myanmar border and if you read these
articles in detail use the the Americans
have a lot of assets on the ground not
only in Burma but also in in mizoram in
Manipur essentially they're all cookie
cookies right
uh yeah so the cookies they have cookie
Assets in Burma and in India there is
this person called
who has
written this article
now if you look at uh
if you if you go deeper into the rabbit
hole you will see this person's
connections to various
so-called Indian intellectuals and all
that so the Americans have their hands
sent deep into this
understand that okay
now um the other geopolitical thing is
is the drug angle
so you have the drug angle and wonder we
one wonders who is controlling that as
well clearly the Burmese government is
not control in the past they must have
been involved in the drug thing but
right now the cookies are doing it so
so it's it's a mess you know so it's
about destabilizing India's Far East
it's about keeping India off balance
it's about creating problems
in India so that India is never stable
and secure it's about making the current
government the current Modi government
look weak and look ineffective
so that it will affect the 2024 election
result all these things are part of
what's going on right now so this is the
geopolitical angle
and it's it's
pretty well it's it's likely that the
U.S and other maybe China also another
Powers Also may have a various levels of
involvement in all this
as you said there is a U.S involvement
in the municipal crisis I didn't I said
there could possibly be a U.S
involvement I did not say there is
please please
learn to listen properly I said there
could possibly perhaps be
some kind of involvement of the US in
the Manipur crisis right that's what I
said please don't
misrepresent what I said okay so even
though it's more beneficial for China
why does the US help China indirectly
remember in Papua New Guinea when Prime
Minister Modi was supposed to go and
have this uh Pacific island nation
Summit the Americans got in the way
remember that a few months ago
they got in the way they tried to uh to
sabotage India's initiative and that
would benefit China the Americans don't
want India to rise too much and they
will help out China in small ways if it
also counterbalances India
so you know that's what they do
so they are okay with helping China
indirectly in some small ways but
overall they want India to counter
balance China in a big way it's it's
complicated but yeah there could be
possibly a U.S involvement like I've
just explained in the Manipur crisis
says what has Prime Minister Modi done
in the last nine years to fix the
problem would you please enlighten us
about it instead of blaming the past
governments listen when when I give you
context it is not blaming the past
governments facts are facts facts don't
care about my feelings or your feelings
or anyone's feelings
I have clearly shown
in this live stream itself how the
problem started it starts with the
British force in the Manipur King to
accept illegal Burmese immigrants you
know settlers
troublemakers it starts with that then
you have the christianization which
happens first before independence with
the British then with the Americans
American missionaries after Independence
then you have the complete neglect and
marginalization of the Northeast which
causes all these insurgencies
and you have the continuous Indian
government's settlement of cookie
refugees into Manipur I showed you
evidence of that so clearly the problem
was created in the 20th century by the
then Indian governments and now in the
last time nine years Mr Modi has come to
power so it's all his fault
think logically I am not saying the
government has not failed right now the
Modi government has failed in the last
two months they should have seen this
coming this is a failure on many levels
they should have seen this coming and
they have failed but let's also look at
what Mr Modi and his government have
done they came to power in Manipur in
2017 at that time Manipur was a disaster
Zone it had seen more than five Decades
of Insurgency
4 pm in the evening when the Sun goes
down in the Far East of India there
would be curfew automatically every
single day
everybody would be off the roads
right there would be bomb blasts
everywhere in Manipur on a routine basis
they would be firing and gunfights
between various Insurgent groups in
Manipur this was happening on a
day-to-day basis even in the city of
imphal itself
until 2016-2017
that's that was the condition in Manipur
after
the BJP came to power they completely
turned around the fortune of the state
okay
by 20 18 2019 there was nightlife in
Manipur
people would go out at night restaurants
and businesses and hotels opened up
in the last five years Manipur was
completely transformed it had started
booming as an economy people were making
money
businesses were operating people who had
left Manipur out of desperation started
returning to Manipur
hotels opened up tourism started moving
Aerosports initiatives started digging
off people and businesses were earning
crores and grows of money
that's what happened in Manipur in the
past five years but this problem was
simmering in the background
and the government should see have seen
this coming the government totally
transformed Manipur in the past five
years from 2017 until 2023.
it was a huge transformation very
positive transformation you could see
this great energy in the state in great
optimism
and then May 3rd onwards we have seen
this sudden spontaneous outbreak of
violence that has pushed back Manipur
two or three decades Manipur has now
gone back to the bad days of the 1990s
and 1980s maybe even worse
so Manipur has been ruined and the
Narendra Modi government should have
seen this coming and clearly they have
failed
so I'm not saying they have not failed
but we also have to understand where the
pro how the problem was created it
wasn't Mr Modi and his government who
created the problem they inherited the
problem
and they have not done a very good job
they had good intentions of Manipur
Manipur was doing so well in the past
five six years
they did what you know they did they did
a lot for Manipur
but now everything has been ruined
and they need to fix it
the vedant says
what do you think about the future of
the Northeast in Manipur is it possible
that India can lose its integral part
because of illegal immigrations illegal
immigrants enforced mass mass
conversions
says will we lose the Far Eastern part
of India I don't think we will lose it
uh territorially
but yes the conversions are still
happening and the people are becoming
alienated from their roots from their
culture and from India
this is something the Chinese have seen
in the 19th century
this is something that Japanese have
written about the samurai wrote about
this when you convert somebody to a
foreign religion they lose their roots
and their allegiance
to their ancestral culture
and then they in some cases become
International that's what the Chinese
and the Japanese have written so Mass
conversion massive industrial scale
demographic religious
uh conversion is an imperialistic and
neocolonialistic Ploy and it has
political
agendas and and motives
and this is something that's happening
so uh even we will definitely not lose
this region territorially
but yes we could lose the hearts and
minds of the people if they if they all
you know lose their their connection
with India
a hundred years ago all the nagas
still practiced their ancestral culture
most of them
most of the misos practice their
ancestral culture polytheistic culture
today they're all
totally different so this is something
that we have allowed to happen it's
something that Mr nehru facilitated and
that is his great legacy we won't lose
the Far East of India but it's going to
be a long hole for us to reintegrate
this region into
the rest of India properly
Niraj mulchandani says clearly there is
an external hand in this issue from the
Myanmar end how hard is it for the
Indian army to repeat the 2015 Myanmar
incidency operation or operation Hot
Pursuit on the Insurgent camps and shut
this matter out completely you know the
Indian army you give them the order if
the government gives them the order they
can solve the entire matter in a matter
of three to seven days
but they have rules of engagement they
are given Rules of Engagement you cannot
do certain things you can not cross
certain lines you can only do these
things and that's why even though all
this is happening there they are forced
to sit and watch
they the Indian army is a very high
quality top quality professional
fighting force they can deal with this
issue in in a short notice
they can you know solve the problems
they can take out all the terrorist
camps
within Burma or wherever it is you think
the Burmese is a government can stop the
Indian army from doing that if we have
to we can do it we can get everything
done quickly
uh
so it's not hard for the Indian army to
do that but if India crosses the border
and undertakes a large scale operation
that lasts let's say three days or five
days in on the territory of a
neighboring country the entire world
will jump on the opportunity to label
India as an expansionist
power evil power same as China you know
that's what they will do so that's why
it doesn't make sense for us to do it
right now unfortunately the root cause
of the problem is in Burma chin State
that's where all the trouble is coming
from
but right now we can't do anything about
that for now at least
two truth shall Prevail 883 says cobrau
Hills and tangjing are where the
original method tribes came down from
the valley to the valley in the ancient
times I think out of the seven clans one
clan came down from the cells and
settled in the valley and later from the
Manipur as you know today that's the
reason why these Hill areas are
considered as sacred places where our
ancestral Divinity resides and these
places have all been desecrated today
yes the Cobra Hill so for the rest of us
who are not from the Northeast think of
it like this
how holy is
it's one of the holiest sites in our
culture and civilization it's currently
in foreign
possession it's it's located in Tibet
which is currently occupied with the
Chinese so Mount kailash one of our
greatest holiest most sacred sites is
under Chinese occupation right now but
they have not the Chinese have not
desecrated kailash they don't allow
anybody to climb the mountain and they
keep everybody off limits they even
allow people to go and pilgrimages and
circum ambulate the mountain
so the Chinese are not desecrating the
mountain now think about something as
holy as that from the perspective of the
people of Manipur the mites for them one
of the holiest places is Mount cobrau
let's let's found let's find it let's
look at it it's north west of imphal
somewhere over here
okay
let's search for it mount
KU
yeah
sit somewhere here
okay let's let's take a look at this
mountain
so this mountain is one of the holiest
and most sacred sites for the methods
the manipuris the money by Hindus and
it's it's kind of the birthplace of of
Manipur is a as a culture as a
civilization and this mountain as you
can see it is kind of becoming bald and
Bolder it's losing its Forest cover it's
because the cookies are now occupying
this place and they are cutting down all
the forests the sacred forests in their
growing poppies there
drug cultivation and you will see Oreo
there's supposed to be a temple over
here right a shrine well do you see any
Shrine here
there is no Shrine here anymore the
shrine has been destroyed guess who did
that
so this sacred place is now off limits
to the methods it has been destroyed and
desecrated
and that's what that's the kind of
cultural genocide that's being done by
the cookies
in Manipur yeah
that's that's the status of the
indigenous people in India today
okay next
boycott something 2779 says the
situation in tripura is also not good
the indigenous Community are not getting
any benefits from the government of
India and the state Plus in the state
and there is infiltration of illegal
illegal bangladeshis and there is
demographic change
Paul Shania says the same situation will
also Prevail in Assam if the illegal
immigration of
bangladeshis is kept unchecked I'm from
Assam it's seen here that most of the
lands are occupied by these people most
of whom have no nrcs even who are not
citizens clearly they were illegal
infiltrators the previous government
failed immensely to stop the illegal
immigration and the same with the
current government even though some
steps are being taken the system has too
many loopholes I don't want to see my
Assam the way like Manipur you will see
the situation across the Far East of
India whether it is tripura whether it
is Assam demographic re-engineering
through massive illegal infiltration
whether it is bangladeshis whether it is
rohingyas or whoever else
the government of India needs to find a
way to solve the problem
we need to find a way to solve this
issue India is not something that's free
for all everybody come in it's a
dharamshala everybody come in and take
our territories and we will give you
special rights and Privileges and we
will and you will allow you to oppress
the true indigenous Indian citizens how
can we have such standards in India it
is high time
that enough is enough and something is
done about this you are seeing a
disaster unfolding right now in real
time in Manipur the same thing Could
Happen very soon in Assam in in tripura
where are the tripuris today the
indigenous people of tripura are the
tripuris how many of them even exist
anymore the place has been totally
demographically re-engenated after 1971.
which was when you had the Bangladeshi
Hindus who had to escape from Bangladesh
the genocide them by the pakistanis and
who came into Bengal in tripura and many
of them settled down there but they were
Hindus but now you have the bangladeshis
who are coming in enormous numbers the
borders are open
tell me something which
which government agency
is in charge of safeguarding India's
borders in the east in Bangladesh in
Bangladesh border it's the border
security Force the BSF
have they done a good job of in carrying
out the duty
the BSF by the way is not the Indian
army it is not the Indian army the
Indian army is one of the world's most
professional and high quality military
forces their standards are unimpeachable
when it comes to the BSF or the crpa for
the Assam rifles
these are Central police forces
these are paramilitary forces they are
not the Indian army they are cops who
wear Army kind of uniforms and who have
automatic rifles and some uh weapons
that typically cops don't have but these
are paramilitary forces these are
Central police forces the BSF is one of
them and the BSF I am sorry to say have
done a terrible job
of preventing
illegal immigration implications they
have completely failed at that and in
the past I can show you Media news
reports on Times of India and wherever
else or BSF officers being being
arrested because they were facilitating
illegal infiltration into India so these
problems the government has to look into
the BSF comes under the central
government
the Assam rifles comes under the central
government there are some rifles is in
charge of
border security in Manipur and I showed
you a document by the government of
Manipur
in which they have asked the Assam
reference for they've asked you know
there are some reference why they
allowed 718
um illegal Burmese aliens cookies to
come into India on the 23rd of May or
23rd of July why
this is what's happening the central
government needs to crack down on the on
the functioning of all these Security
Forces paramilitary forces who are
tasked with safeguarding India's border
security and who are failing in their
job it's it's terrible it's very very
disappointing that this is happening
so the same situation exists across the
Far East of India the northeast of India
Manipur is a disaster zone now Assam we
know what's happening there tripura
tripuris hardly exists anymore you know
they've lost their own ancestral
territory that's a whole other disaster
at least we don't have ethnic cleansing
in terrorism in tripura right now
Manipur you have it openly right now and
through
so that's the situation okay next
what can be the way forward for Manipur
the simple thing is we need to do in a
nursing get rid of all the aliens
and we need to have a proper cutoff date
for the NRC
so it cannot be let's compromise and
let's keep the cutoff date at 2001 or
maybe 1991 no Manipur became a part of
the union union of India in 1949 if
there is any justice in the world the
cutoff date for the energy should be
1949 or at the the latest at the most
1951. and anybody who is in Manipur
especially the the Burmese origin people
they should be able to prove that they
or their ancestors
were living in Manipur before 1949 or
1951 whichever date we take they have to
be able to show evidence of that if they
can't show evidence they have to be
deported back to their Homeland engine
state where they can fight for an
imaginary country it's not our problem
in India
everybody's problem is not our problem
so the way forward is a proper NRC and
it should be done properly if just
because somebody has another cut doesn't
mean that their Indians an Indian
Citizen and just because the Burmese
origin person has an Indian passport
doesn't mean that they should be
included as a citizen we have to go back
and dig deep into the antecedents you're
getting other cards at eight thousand
rupees a piece now once you have another
card you can get a passport so that is
not the way to do things the NRC in
Assam Muslim was a mess if I recall
correctly it did not go well
a more
natives were were listed as foreigners
than infiltrators the infiltrators all
had the documents and the natives did
not have the other documents in Assam so
that's not the way to do it in our thing
you leave it to the bureaucrats they're
going to mess everything up it has to be
done properly so the way forward is
either so NRC has to be done foreigners
have to be ejected from Burma from
Manipur that's the only way you will
have Justice you can either give in to
the blackmail and the violence of the of
the of the of the intolerant oppressor
or you have Justice and you give Justice
to the natives by ejecting the illegals
you cannot give in to violence you
cannot give in to Blackmail you do it
once you will embolden
these guys and they will want more and
more
so the way forward is NRC get rid of all
the aliens and then if required fence
the Border it will take maybe a few
years do it
or
you know maybe conduct a military
operation in the chin State and get you
know and neutralize all the terrorists
that could be another thing which we
could perhaps do uh in cooperation with
the Burmese government that's where the
problem is coming from from chin state
so these are some of the things we could
do but right now Manipur is ruined
the BJP government took Manipur forward
a great deal from 2017 to 2023 23 but in
the past two and a half months Manipur
has gone backwards two or three decades
and whatever damage has been done it is
not just 100 or maybe thousands of
crores of rupees maybe lacks of course
of Base not just that entire businesses
have been ruined entire crops have been
destroyed and the entire state has been
pushed back by several decades
and it's going to take at least a decade
to undo the damage so the government has
failed
there are no two ways about it the
government has failed it's very
disappointing and they need to find the
solution ASAP as soon as possible so I
think that's that's all I had with the
questions I I had lots of other
questions but I took 25 and I think I've
answered them all now let's see if we
have any uh
questions in the live chat I can take
maybe two or three questions from the
live chat
uh so in case you have questions which I
have not taken which I've not taken
today uh ask them in the live chat and
I'll take maybe two or three of these
and the questions have to be about
Manipur not other things
all right today is Manipur
uh I have answered this question I have
answered this question
uh I'm not taking ISRO drdo today
uh
okay do we have any interesting
questions that have not taken today
people asking questions about something
else
reign of the Reina queen of Queens says
locals and informants
Village witnessed a strange bright light
hovering high up in the sky between 7 pm
and 8 pm on September 18. I suppose the
cookies have UFOs now flying saucers
or maybe the Americans are involved
what can I say
uh
uh keshav says why are some Soo groups
which means cookie terrorist groups so
beloved to the minister of Home Affairs
that the state straight up rejected
Manipur state governments appeal to
revoke the so I listen I don't know
what's happening I don't know what the
government is doing and what the logic
is the Manipur state government
obviously we know that they wanted to
revoke the soo the suspension of
operation agreement but looks like the
central government has not gone ahead
with that
I don't know what the calculations are
and all that obviously I I still trust
the government of India and I know that
they prioritize the national interests
about everything but sometimes the
national interest takes a few years to
fructify
so I don't know what it is but yeah it's
it's
storyboard
Savannah I have answered this for two
hours
you can look look back at the live
stream and you know I have answered all
this
okay what next
okay World gaming says
why is the Indian BSF so useless
yeah well that's something the central
government needs to look into it comes
under the central government the BSF has
totally failed in curbing any kind of
illegal infiltration from Bangladesh we
have lacks maybe millions of illegal
Bangladeshi infiltrators all across
India
and they have failed
so I don't know why they are so useless
but they are and it is something for the
central government to fix and thus far
nothing has been done it's frustrating
and it deeply disappointing
survive the Mathers Will Survive they've
been around for thousands of years and
they will run for a few thousand years
more at least
it's a bad time everybody understands
but you got to be strong
and you go to well do what it takes
am I am I learning French no I learned
French a long long long long long long
long long time ago
okay
which what will happen to politics in
Manipur now which party will come to
power so I think the people of Manipur
especially the methods are extremely
disenchanted and disillusioned with the
BJP government it's possible that the
Congress may come to power next time
it's possible I'm not saying it will but
possible and please remember who created
the Manipur problem in the first place I
would I would
I would encourage the people of Manipur
to look at history and understand who
created this problem in the first place
was it the BJP or was it the Congress
then vote wisely I know the BJP
government has done made a mess of
things
but
the problem was not of their making
and maybe it was too big for them to
solve right now maybe it will take a
decade to solve they will solve it
but it's going to take time
uh why how how are the cookies getting
so much media favor well they belong to
a special religion
they come from outside they get special
privileges
right so obviously the media will favor
them that's how it is that's
unfortunately how it is
says is there any land for cookies in
the world listen it's not my problem
whether they have any land for
themselves or not the cookies are not my
people they are not indians
they whether they have land or not is
not India's problem
so they have chin state where they live
and they're trying they're fighting the
government there why I don't know
they have a land which is chin state in
Burma
okay let's let's once again go there
chin State okay chin state this huge
piece of territory is where these
cookies live
so why do they want more in more
territory
so they're behaving exactly like the
People's Republic of China
that's the same attitude that they have
they already have this land but they're
not satisfied they want more and more
they want huge chunks of India they want
to cut off the entire Forest of India
from Southeast Asia and they also want
pieces of Bangladesh that's how much
territory they want for themselves
I have no sympathy for people who are
rapacious expansionist and who want to
steal other people's land and and do
whatever they've been doing
okay
are we done
uh this says even Maite will not be able
to show proofs of having lived in
Manipur before 1949. I would say that
the method should not be required to
show proofs everyone knows
the historical record is very clear the
methods are the original people of
Manipur but they should not be required
to show proof only the Burmese origin
people should be required to make to
show proof nagas and methods should not
be required to show proof of having
stayed in Manipur before 1949. only the
Burmese should be required to show proof
if there is any justice
all right
okay I think I'm done for today
I hope it was it it was informative it
hopefully it showed
many maybe clarify the situation a
little bit a little bit more
so yeah I'm gonna end this live stream
now it's already crossed two hours well
past two hours so thank you very much
all of you for all your questions and uh
I will see you soon hopefully in the
next live stream until then take care
and like I always say keep raising your
standards thank you very much good day
good night wherever you are and I'll see
you soon bye